[Music]
what's up everyone
i hope you're as excited as i am to talk
a whole bunch about muscle hypertrophy
before we get started i need to
apologize i know my voice sounds a bit
weird
i've just been dealing with a couple of
weeks of a very very nasty case of the
gains yeah i know
you loved it well if you like my friend
chris here
and you like me right every one of us
that i know is interested in some point
to maximizing their muscle gains and you
may be thinking to yourself
hey andy i know that muscle physiology
is your area of expertise you study
how muscle fibers grow shrink dye and
repair in your lab and you've been doing
that for a decade
but you may not realize i actually used
to be a competitive bodybuilder
back in the day in fact i was actually
pretty famous before there was even
instagram in those things and
i used to get fans come up to me all the
time asking me for pictures and you can
see like a good example that here this
guy right up was like hey man can i get
a double biceps picture and i'm like
sure
you know so i was kind enough to take a
picture of him with it and
um you know anyways if you
you want to actually see a picture of me
my one of my competitions all right well
here it is i was a little more tan and
just a little
a little bit more muscular in this
picture here but this is
this is a local meet that i did one time
i didn't win you know obviously
i thought i got second place that was
pretty good
well anyways uh and humans in general
we've been interested in strength
training and gaining muscle
for a really long time in fact there's
documents suggesting that we've been
lifting muscle
or lifting weights for the purpose of
growing muscle since the 7th century
there's a really cool article here by
the famous
sport historian jan todd on the history
of barbells and dumbbells and when women
started lifting with dumbbells and
things like that that
i encourage you to explore but we've
actually been studying muscle growth
with exercise for almost 100 or over 100
years now
the first study came out in the late
1800s
by a german scientist and he actually
threw a couple of dogs
on a treadmill what he did is he
actually cut one of those sartorius
muscles out of their leg
put them on a treadmill for two months
and then looked at how much
their other assault areas grew and found
about a 50
increase in hypertrophy after just
treadmill running for a couple of months
so the point being we've spent a lot of
time and effort
as a society as scientists and as
individuals
trying to understand how to maximize
muscle growth for a very long time
and if you've been up to date with the
field or you've seen any of my previous
work
especially some of my podcasts with
barbell shrugged and stuff years ago
you may feel like you got a pretty good
grip on the science but what i want to
actually do and the reason
i'm making all these videos is we have
learned a tremendous amount in the last
three years alone
on what muscle hypertrophy actually is
what causes it
and then how to then maximize it with
your training and hypertrophy
so i've decided to do this giant video
series on all things hypertrophy
in part one like i said i'll describe
some of the newest things we've learned
in just the last couple of years in fact
several of the things i've included in
that video came out just within a month
of me filming this
so i'll talk in depth about what we know
uh scientifically
about what actually is muscle
hypertrophy what parts grow which ones
don't how much
etc part two then i'll get into the
stimuli and it causes the molecular
mechanisms
if you like the biochemistry piece uh
the molecular biology side of it
video two is your jam and then part
three is when i'll specifically get into
the eating and training to maximize
so if you just want the practical
applications you want to know how much
volume you should be hitting what order
to do your exercises in
frequency uh what type e center
concentric
drop sets pyramids which ones work
better all that stuff
that's all in video three but i actually
i think you should start with at least
video two because
you'll never really truly understand uh
how to train
to optimize growth if you don't
understand what's causing
your body to want to grow muscle in the
first place
um well what i'll also do is i'll try to
chop these up into some 5-minute ones as
well but
if you want the full jam my strongest
recommendation start at one go to two
go to three and you'll all understand as
much as we could possibly give you
on all things muscle hypertrophy okay
enjoy let's have a fun ride here and
let's get a little bit more
jacked all right maybe i should stop i
don't know when i look better
so let's get started with part one of
this series and talk about the
physiology
of muscle growth and all the really
interesting things we've learned in just
the last couple of years
scientifically on muscle hypertrophy so
just to give you a framework i want to
first talk about the very basics of what
a muscle is and how it works before we
move on to
some of the latest signs so you know
that skeletal muscle has a huge
array of functions in the muscle or in
the human body
well in fact if we step back and just
look at what the human body is in
general
it's about 50 water and 40 muscle
everything else is only 10 or so that's
how big a deal muscle is
and we know that if you're an exercise
scientist like me that you tend to
associate with
muscle with things like movement as well
right this is the thing that moves us so
if you're
if you're in a sport you have to be
entered into muscle there's no other way
and so there's some very pragmatic
reasons that you may want to understand
muscle hypertrophy but there's also some
ones that are
i guess pragmatic in a different way but
let's be real some of us just
want to look better so all these things
i've talked about here are a matter of
function right you want to have better
posture in your immune system to work
better and
better endocrine system and all that but
you sometimes want to just
look better for the purposes of vanity
and i'm totally down with that train too
so it's really important in fact i i one
of the reasons i love muscle so much is
i don't see how you can get through life
without paying attention to it in fact
it's
it's a central thing to me because it
drives so many factors
in fact if you look at the literature
that it's estimated we spend about 25
billion dollars a year on muscle wasting
diseases
so again you know i think sport i think
aesthetics
first but let's not forget that this is
really important for all of us to pay
attention to
if we can improve how our understanding
of how to maintain and improve muscles
quality
and size we could put a serious dent in
that 25 million
deficit as well as reduce some of the
suffering folks are
going through because of muscle wasting
diseases
now another reason i like muscle
hypertrophy training
is because it is so well-rounded in
terms of the outcome
yes you get you look bigger and that's
great but physiologically it's about the
strongest bang for your buck training
system you could possibly get
so here's an example of a chart that i
have now this is actually laid out and
described in a separate video i think
one of my endurance videos
but on the top horizontally i've laid
out the different types of training that
one can do
so you could train and get faster you
could get better endurance you could
improve your strength etc
and on the vertical i've got the
different physiological things that are
altered with that type of training
for an example there you wouldn't expect
to see many changes in your vo2 max with
just pure speed training or power
training
you're not going to really see an
improvement in your bone mineral density
by getting better at shooting free
throws and developing physical skill
okay and so some types of training
influence some physiological systems but
not
others and as i mentioned the beauty of
hypertrophy training is
it ticks all the boxes and it ticks them
a lot
and so again just from a pragmatic
perspective if you're just trying to
train to be generally healthy
this is a place we should probably spend
a decent amount of time
bang for your buck okay
so how do you actually get the
adaptation i know that some of you that
have
probably skipped this part of the video
you've gone to video three where i talk
about the outcome stuff
well if we want to understand how to get
bigger and add more muscle we first have
to understand well what are we even
talking about
what actually is growing what are we
trying to get to first
and that's the physiology so in this
specific video
i'm going to talk about a whole bunch of
things first and foremost
how much do muscles grow what's an
anticipated amount
is the growth uniform across the entire
muscle then i'm actually going to show
you really soon here
a whole bunch of images of actual real
tissue from professional athletes
we'll go over the sliding filament
theory very briefly in myofiber
lengthening
i'll also finally give in i've been
teasing this for years
about i'll outline my views on muscle
fiber splitting or
hyperplasia myofiber growth i will talk
about the difference between like what
we call
bodybuilding induced muscle growth
versus power lifting
and then i'll finish by talking about
sarcoplasmic hypertrophy
and i have a special challenge for all
of you
those of you ambitious folks at the very
end of the video
so let's jump into it let's start
talking about how much muscle actually
grows
okay so you know if you did
some training you know you train for two
months or three months how much would
you realistically expect your muscle to
grow
well we tend to see something like five
to twenty percent in the first couple of
months of training
if somebody did a study and they
published 20 weeks of training and they
saw three percent
group improvement in size i would
probably question whether or not
actually much happened inverse if i saw
somebody improved
50 or they wrote on an instagram post
and they had a 50
increase in their muscle size after
three months of training
i'd probably be incredibly skeptical
okay now that's not impossible but those
are not the norms this is what we're
generally looking for
in terms of where the muscle is growing
we don't see it necessarily always being
uniform throughout an individual muscle
so if you take say the biceps muscles
here and there's several biceps muscles
but
you just pick one of them your favorite
one if you did three months of training
you might see that say the middle of the
muscle increases
by 20 percent but this portion and that
portion only grow by maybe 10 percent or
it could be the inverse the point is
it's not the exact same throughout the
entire portion of the muscle
now we don't exactly know what's going
on here we don't know how robust or true
this finding actually is because we have
fairly limited information on it and so
i put a little bit of a tbd
here we don't exactly know what causes
or how real of a finding that is in part
three though i do talk about how this
probably is a reason why we do need to
have slight variation in our training
for example not always doing your bicep
curl the exact same way
because that might actually cause that
non-uniform muscle growth
in fact i don't really have time to get
into it these videos are long enough as
it is
but i think this is an actual artifact
of limited science
so i think if we did more variation in
the types of exercises we use
scientifically
we would resolve this issue we tend to
just say okay
you want to grow your quad do leg
extensions on the exact same leg
accenture machine well
we're probably only going to cause
growth at a certain spot
anyways i'll talk more about that in
video three the practical application
section
okay so what exactly is hypertrophying
then we know it's the muscle we know
it's happening
at different areas but what's inside of
the muscle that's actually growing
is the major point of this first video
okay now before we do that i really
encourage you to stop and go take a look
at this really nice paper
this is my mike roberts at auburn and
he's just a fantastic muscle physiology
scientist he is doctoral student cody
han published this paper
a year or so ago and i talked about how
even that term muscle hypertrophy is
fairly confusing
scientifically we don't have agreement
on what that actually means
so for example you could do a study and
do a pre and post bod pod on somebody
you know and that kind of gives you a
measure of muscle hypertrophy and then
you could call that
growth well that's actually probably
very different than if you take an
ultrasound image
and trace the actual muscle size and
that's quite different than if you took
a biopsy and looked at how much protein
is inside the myofiber
and we don't necessarily we have strong
disagreement
with all three of those measures so as
you go through the literature for the
scientific kind of person or you're
paying attention or you
you at least follow people on social
media who put up scientific stuff
this can cause some confusion so make
sure you pay attention to this and go
look at their definitions of what muscle
hypertrophy actually is and how we
should talk about it the nomenclature
it's a very easy article to read even if
you're not a super scientist
okay but that aside getting back to it
if we took one of those individual bicep
muscles of brachii or brachialis or
whatever you wanted to do
you'd realize that each individual
muscle is made up of millions of
of small muscle cells now you can use
the term muscle fiber muscle cell
or myo mild meeting muscle myofiber
interchangeably those are the same thing
i'll try to stick with muscle fiber
but that's all the same thing okay so if
you were to come in with a needle
into that biceps muscle whichever one
you picked grab some of those
muscle fibers and pull them out and
start to look at them
this is what it would look like now i'm
going to give special bonus points to
any of you on youtube
or anyone on instagram or wherever that
can see the little joke i just made
there
i'm not going to tell you tell me i'll
you'll make me smile a lot if you figure
it out and you can use
hey it was anyways
this is what it actually looks like okay
so this is me actually going in with a
little biopsy needle and you can see the
the participants laying on us back there
and that's his left quad
and i go in with that needle you're
seeing on the right and we take um
you know about a hundred milligrams a
muscle there looks like a nice piece of
tartar right
it's delicious sushi if you so that's
the actual muscle
so what it looks like uh when we bring
it out it's pretty painless and it
doesn't cause any injuries i've had like
almost 40 on myself i've done
thousands of them now on people they're
pretty
light on the risk and this is what it
would look like so if i took that little
circle right here from the middle and i
pulled that out and i set it right on
that petri dish right behind you
and then i line all the muscle fibers up
and you can see in fact that image on
the
your left i think that's all that's
actually tissue from a world champion
and i won't tell you
who or what sport but yeah
that's that's what that's what actual
muscle fibers look like so each one of
those bundles has
maybe a couple hundred fibers or so in
it and then we straighten them all out
so we could
analyze them and take a look at it so
what we do is we put it in a special
solution and it takes it from
red like you see in the top corner there
to kind of white in the bottom corner it
just makes it easy for us to kind of
isolate them but what you see up here is
you know a bundle like that and then
there's
you know a dozen or so fibers and then
those are the individual ones
right there so if you want to see what
that actually looks like i've dyed the
fiber green here
to make it easier to see and up the top
there with the needles
i'm going to pull out a couple of
individual muscle fibers just with some
tweezers
and there you go okay in fact i got two
there so you watch i'll separate them
and pull them
away from each other and there we are
all right so if i took one of those
individual muscle fibers and i took it
to one of my really nice expensive
microscopes i could put it in three
dimension
and start to analyze it so you're seeing
a rotating three-dimensional view
of an individual muscle fiber there the
blue stuff is the nuclei
all right but you can see we could then
take images of it and study a whole
bunch of things like how long it is how
thick it is
and we could dye it for anything you
wanted basically mitochondria or
in this case mononuclei or really
whatever we wanted
in fact i could even take that image and
go to any 3d printer
print it and it would look something
like that all right so that's a plastic
plaster if you will um of that
individual that same exact fiber just
slightly different colors because the
printer didn't have those same colors
okay well let's let's talk a little bit
more about the the basic physiology
of the muscle fiber and so then we can
talk about what parts specifically grow
how much and
and if different styles of training
cause different types of growth
well if you took one of those those
muscles uh the biceps if you will
and you imagine that to be that blue
circle so now we're looking at this in
what we call cross-sectional area
a cross-section rather and we've got all
those
red individual muscle fibers and you can
see they're kind of laid out throughout
the entire
muscle well those are actually wrapped
around together and
made into little bundles that we call
fascicles okay now i'm going to
eliminate these
from the equation just because i i'm
going to try to keep this as simple and
straightforward as possible but don't
forget
the fibers themselves are bundled
together in fascicles and that is
important
um that's sear endomysium perimysin and
epimysium if you've had some anatomy or
physiology before
and they're very very important to force
transfer
and strength out and reinforce
development things like that but for
growth
since that's just connective tissue i'm
going to take it out of the equation
okay now in in each individual muscle
fiber
we see actually a whole bunch of things
called myofibrils
now this is why i'm going to try to
avoid calling the muscle fibers
myofibers because then we'd have to keep
in your brain myofibers versus
myofibrils
so i'm going to try to say muscle fiber
versus myofibril
so just like you have a bunch of muscle
fibers inside your muscle you've got a
bunch of myofibrils inside each muscle
fiber
and then they look kind of like that now
actually a better view more realistic
view is this so this is another paper
published recently by
mike roberts and cody han and they did a
really nice job describing it so you can
follow the images below
so you can see that horizontal muscle
fiber and if you cut it and look it
in cross section you can see that the
brown circle on the outside is the
sarcolemma or the cell membrane
you can see the myonuclei right up there
these other little blue
circles are the mitochondria and then
all those little gray circles are
actually myofibrils so in this image i'm
representing there being four myofibrils
per muscle fiber but in reality there's
probably thousands and so mike and cody
have done a much better job representing
what it actually looks like here
so if you zoom in on any of those
myofibrils like they've done here
and look at it you can see that each
myofibril is surrounded by the
sarcoplasmic reticulum
which gives its calcium for contraction
glycolytic enzymes and a bunch of other
things like that right so in fact if you
go to the further image you can actually
see a real image of what it would look
like
so you can see the myofibrils in green
there and each one is surrounded by
the sarcoplasmic reticulum and the
mitochondria in red so those aren't
muscle fibers like we typically see when
we show you cross sections
that's actually zoomed way in and that's
just looking at the myofibrils within
one muscle cell itself so
great job with mike and cody the really
nice paper and a great image to help you
learn that
okay now within each myofibril
we've got another chunk of things called
myofilaments
now the myofilaments are broken up into
two categories actin
and myosin and you can see that in the
in the center there
you've got one myosin surrounded by six
actin all right
now those are the things that reach up
and grab each other get pulling closer
together that cause a muscle to contract
and stack on top of each other
and look like that okay so
again i'm just representing there's
actually a whole bunch of myosin and
actin in each myofibril but i'm just
representing you the concept
okay another paper and i promise i'll
start using other authors pretty soon
here but
a different paper by mike and cody
really nice job
where they outlined some of the basic
physiology so this is exactly what i
just talked to you about
about a different view because
visualization is really important with
this stuff
you can see the whole muscle over there
they've even also outlined the fascicle
like i talked about
zoomed in farther to the individual
muscle fibers you can see how those
pollen and myofibrils
and those pull into the myofilaments so
you can see the myofilaments the myosin
actin actin
put together you can see this kind of
like z
line ding ding ding ding ding ding ding
ding ding so that space
to that space is called the sarcomere
and so you can see up here in the image
when they say sarcomere
in series is you'd have another one of
these right here
and then another one right there and
they would go longitudinally
throughout the thing okay so that would
be what we call sarcomere in series
so if you stack them next to each other
one bubble not on top
in order like that that's called in
series and that's important to
understanding how the muscle fiber grows
which we'll talk about
in detail in a second here so this is
what i'm talking about
again imagine one of those sarcomeres
next to each other well one
way you could potentially hypertrophy is
to simply add another one in series
so making the entire cell longer
all right the other way to do it would
be to add sarcomeres in parallel
so then instead of stacking at the end
you stack it on top
and that would make it thicker okay so
now because we know
muscles don't run from one end
or muscle fibers all the way from one
end of origin to the other end of
insertion
let me explain so imagine your biceps
muscle started right there
and it ended right there okay now
depending on which biceps muscle we're
talking about they have different origin
and different insertion points let's
just say it started right there and
right there
well a muscle fiber might run the entire
length but it might also
not and so you still have the ability to
add
more in series to increase the length of
it or
you could add within the muscle fiber
more of these sarcomeres on top and it
would stack and get thicker and thicker
so that's what we mean when we say
sarcomeres in series could add
hypertrophy
as well as sarcomeres in parallel they
could
increase the overall volume of the
muscle
in different ways by either adding
length or by adding thickness
both of those could theoretically be
options
okay so just again to visualize it in a
little bit different fashion there
this would be one individual muscle
fiber this entire picture
and they're zoomed in really nicely on
those myofibrils
and in fact if you zoom in those
myofibrils even more you can see those
little
dots which they're representing to be
the myofilaments
actin and myosin
okay so if we come back to this
particular image here
oh those you can see those myosin and
actin and you can see that they're
representing
myosin and actin in 2d so you can see
the myosin in the middle and then the
actin kind of on top well actually
this is kind of what looked like if
you've never had the sliding sliding
filament theory this is it real fast
so the myosin that black stuff right in
here
the acting out here so this is red and
this is green
acting as green in my next image like
that so this is really what it looks
like what basically happens is
you've got atp the energy currency of
the cell on the head of the myosin
filament
so that gets hydrolyzed and split that
gives you some energy some calcium comes
in from the sarcoplasmic reticulum
the myosin reaches up grabs the actin
goes to what's called a power stroke and
pulls the actin forward
very condensed version okay well in
reality of it is like i said there's
about six actin surrounding
uh each myosin so wouldn't this look
like this one to one ratio
it would actually look more like that
okay
and so if you can imagine those little
globular heads coming off of the side
of all aspects of that myosin it could
reach up and grab
any actin and pull it in this case
towards you
or away from you okay
so that's what we're looking like and
again we call those the myofilaments
actin
and myosin together are the myofilaments
so the muscle fibers themselves if you
look at it and it's towards like
its diameter we typically call that as a
cross-sectional area so how much area is
it when we look at it in cross-section
and one of the reasons we do that is
because we can't biopsy and look at the
entire fiber
like i said the sartorius actually is
some of those fibers run the entire
length from your hip to your knee
so i'd have to remove the entire muscle
to get the entire muscle
fiber so what we do is we go and we take
a chunk of it we flip it sideways
and we look at the cross section just to
see how wide it is because we have no
idea how long
it actually is but you can see the
values
for how thick a muscle fiber can be and
as i kind of mentioned earlier
human skeletal muscle are some of the
biggest cells by volume in all of
biology
and they probably have the most nuclei
they're multi-nucleated
but it's not a couple it's a lot so it's
really really
special tissue that we have and then you
can see the amount of force
produced by each individual
muscle fiber as well as each individual
myosin filament themselves
so some pretty cool stuff there if
you're interested now this is another
way
so you what you're actually seeing there
is not mild uh fibroids but an actual
whole muscle so this is a bunch of
muscle fibers here
so each blue circle there outlines a new
muscle fiber so you're looking at i
don't know what 50 year
something like that 25 muscle fibers on
here that's one
that's one that's one and
uh this is from my colleague jimmy
bagley who does just a great amount of
work in the area of muscle physiology as
well
up in san francisco so the green ones
he's
the type two the fastest muscle fibers
he's dyed green
and the slow twitch muscle fibers he's
dyed yellow so what we typically see is
the fastest muscle fibers are generally
bigger than the slow choice ones but not
always
we see a very strong just natural
variability i mean look at the image
there
not all fibers are the same size you can
see some really large
slow stretch fibers there and then some
kind of small faster fibers
but in general if you were to average
all of these fibers across the sample
across multiple biopsy samples you would
generally see the fastest fibers
averaging to be
slightly bigger than the slow church but
we also have a huge training influence
so one of the things that jimmy and i
have seen now
um dealing with hundreds of thousands of
muscle fibers
is if you do a lot of steady state
endurance you get preferential
hypertrophy of the slow fibers
or potentially preferential atrophy of
the fast fibers however you want to look
at it
you do strength training and we see
preferential growth of the fast fiber so
your
your training background really
significantly influences
the size of each muscle fiber in its in
its type
okay so uh
another really really awesome article
that came out just a couple of years ago
here
and they effectively dove into what's
called the proteome or the protein part
on the muscle fibers so
there's some really cool stuff we
learned from that project that i'm going
to talk about here
but if we look at the individual muscle
fiber itself we do see that about 75
of it is water in fact um if you'd
actually eat meat
like you eat steak and stuff we
typically talk about that as being like
water yeah so actually when your muscles
aqueous when you're when you're not
eating it because remember when you cook
it you dry it out a little bit so you
lose some water
but in general your muscle is mostly
water and the remaining 25 percent
is is broken up in what we call proteins
okay about of that 25 about 15 of that
are called myofibular
and about 5 of that is sarcoplasmic and
i'll talk more in depth about that later
but
the general way to break that down is
myofibular means
it's coming in the part of either an
actin or myosin and sarcoplasmic just
means it's
um in between that and the cell membrane
right so the outside
the cell wall if you will of the muscle
right it's it's a membrane because it's
a human if it's a plant we call it wall
pretty similar though okay so proteins
in those different areas
uh break that up now that doesn't
complete
everything that's in a muscle but it's
the vast majority of what we can talk
about today
another important thing here about 40 of
proteins
that we have seen in the muscle fibers
are for metabolism and only about 10
percent are for contraction
and so most of the things that are in
your muscle
are there to help you produce energy and
a little bit to cause contraction
a little side note here again these
numbers are relative not concentration
so make sure you pay attention to that
if you're doing some
serious muscle physiology but that's
really what we're looking at
okay so if you're to break the muscle
fiber itself up
about 50 of the proteins in your muscle
fiber are myosin
about 20 percent are actin all right and
about 10
are called titan and titan's a giant
protein probably the largest protein we
have in our body
and it kind of holds the myosin in place
so that you can contract and not
be contracting all over the place if you
will about 5
our nebulin nebulin is kind of like the
equivalent of titan but from the actin
so it's
kind of holds the acting in place
troponin tropomyosin which are the
things that you use
on actin you know from the sliding
filament theory and then a small
percentage are the
things that are in the sarcoplasmic
reticulum the mitochondria t-tubules and
things like that
okay so that's basically what we're
looking at that's what's made that's
what muscle is actually made of
in general so now that we understand the
basics of the physiology
let's start talking about what the
science shows us in terms of what grows
and how with hypertrophy training as i
mentioned in the introduction this video
we've been studying muscle exercise
induced muscle growth
for over 120 years scientifically and in
fact if you go back to that original
study
uh by dr morpurgo we've actually found
that
in general we think of muscle
hypertrophy being an increase in that
cross section rather than
hyperplasia okay so if you think about
it this way the only way a muscle could
grow would be to either
increase the size of its individual
fibers or to increase the number of
muscle fibers
we've been telling folks for decades and
hundreds of years now actually that
it comes entirely from an increase in
cross-sectional area and there is no
addition of new muscle fibers or no
hyperplasia
okay if you've ever i know you've been
taught that this is the genesis of that
thought process
this original paper and in general that
has held true people
continue to reiterate that same thing
but as we'll see later
maybe some holes in that maybe not maybe
okay so update now a great study came
out again just this july
by again two more you know true
legendary muscle scientists
stu phillips up in canada has done a ton
of stuff in this area but really
uh sorry sue sorry stu but troy
hornberger
is just done so much work in this area
he's the guy that really drove this
particular paper
and so i'll give him credit so it's
really nice also a paper that's fairly
easy to read
that's not super easy but if you have
some training in this field
you won't find it particularly difficult
to read they did a really nice job of
reviewing what it actually looks like
for muscles to grow so a large part of
what i'm going to present is a breakdown
of this paper
as well as some other things so
congratulations troy
and stu you've made my youtube videos
the world famous andy galp in 55 minute
phase videos
your careers are finally you've made it
guys
congrats who knows i could get six
eight maybe even 900 views on this video
it's a big deal i know
big deal okay so
in the next hour or whatever it's going
to take me i'm going to break down
all the possible ways the muscle can
grow and then show you how much
scientific evidence we have behind them
so first possible way as i mentioned
briefly is
length the actual muscle could grow in
length so that would be this
so the muscle fibers themselves do that
and i already explained to you a little
bit about how that can manifest itself
and how that'd be possible
so now here's a little bit of a
visualization this is not exactly what
happens but
this is what could happen so in the
image i'm sort of depicting that the
muscle fibers they like that but in
reality that's not actually how they do
so muscle fibers don't lie in parallel
to the muscle itself
they typically have what's called a
penation angle so the angle
that's that's the angle at which they
actually come off so it may actually
look like that so even though the muscle
looks like it's running this way the
fibers may actually run at an angle
if they run more parallel to it that's a
smaller penis and angle if they turn and
run more horizontal or perpendicular to
it that's a larger penetration angle
so what can happen is and one of the
things we know happens pretty routinely
is we see increases in ponation angle by
about seven to 15 percent or so
with hypertrophy type of training so
that angle changes
so you can imagine going from that to
like that
or the inverse right if we went down it
was more
in sync with the muscle that would allow
us to change the length of the actual
fibers because
we can move them a little bit so like i
said
if we were to do it that way and the the
penetration angle changed that way the
muscle fiber would actually have to grow
vertically in order for it to fit the
entire thing so that could still explain
why your bicep is larger even though you
just increased your length
because you also had a constant increase
or change in pinnation angle with
generally being an increase
okay now this is really tricky because
the penetration angle is different with
almost every single muscle so it's very
complicated here
i'm just giving you a general idea and
trying to show you conceptually how this
could work
well this change in venetian angle like
i said it's pretty robust it seems to
happen
pretty commonly in the research so
not a one or two off kind of thing a
pretty standard finding
but so because of that we also then
can theorize uh that we would see an
increase in fascicle length and this is
actually something that's pretty easy to
measure the ultrasound
and you see this again pretty commonly
we've done this in my lab as well
that the fascicle length increases with
hypertrophy
because of this angle change that allows
it to go along so
let me be very clear the muscle itself
is not growing
in terms of length so if the entire
muscle went from here to here
you're not growing longer you're not
changing the origin or insertion point
you are taking the fascicles though and
causing them to lengthen because you're
changing their angle
in which they sit with the muscle so
that explains how you could have an
increase in information angle or
decrease or whatever
a change in fascicle length but the
muscle didn't grow longer so the muscle
fascicles grew longer but not the
muscles per se in fact the muscular
fascicles going longer
increase cross-sectional area but not
muscle length
all right very common confusion there so
what we are unaware of though is if the
muscle
fibers themselves change length like i
mentioned it's pretty impossible for us
to actually figure that thing out
i'm not sure how you could do that
it would be difficult for us to measure
the entire
fascicle like that so i don't think
we're ever going to know the answer to
whether or not the entire fascicle gets
longer
at this point we have to just look at
hey the fascicle length
gets there but we wouldn't we would
never be able to capture
now without the fibers are getting
longer that's going to be pretty
impossible
okay so another way to think about it is
this
so theoretically one way that we could
do this is
by adding sarcomeres and lengthening the
monofiber again this is theoretical
that's why there's a question there
because we can't do it
but you can see again from that really
nice paper
images of what that could look like so
if you see on the left here
or we'll just start right here imagine
you've got that sarcomere okay and this
is
standard happen well if you started to
increase and to grow a new sarcomere in
the middle here
eventually you could get that serial
increase in sarcomere
number and that would
increase the length of the mild fiber
okay the image is actually shown over
here you can see that as well
so you can see damage starting to happen
there it's getting all shaky there and
you can see a new
sarcomere starting to grow from the
middle and causing it to extend
out so i there's there's some like
evidence to suggest that actually may
happen
if that did happen we would have our
increase in serial length of sarcomeres
and resulting increase in length of the
myofibers
so like we said i'm going to still put a
question mark there because we don't
know that this specifically happens
and we certainly don't know what happens
in humans with things like you know with
lifting weights other animal models and
stuff like that maybe indicate hey this
may happen but we
still haven't really don't have a really
good explanation
of fibers but this happening in humans
yet
um some people think actually may be
growing at different spots so in this
case they're guessing it grows in the
middle
but we don't know that for sure it could
grow at the middle and
or some other place in the fiber we
don't know all right so hopefully maybe
in a few years i'll redo this video and
we'll have an answer to that but
probably not
difficult question for us to get to
okay so
another way to think about this is okay
here's the image if you've got the
muscle belly there
and you increase the length of the
sarcomeres in series
and because they don't run the entire
length you can see how in this great
illustration
how that would actually make the muscle
fiber itself grow larger
okay so now there's a reason why there's
a check there is because again we know
the fascicle length goes up we know
ponition angle does
we just don't know how it works in the
mild fiber so yes to the fascicle
we don't know yet about the muscle cell
itself all right so again that would be
your sarcomere increase in
series that i i laid out earlier if we
come back to our
scorecard here that we're starting we
can see we got a kind of a length
a yes and no for length explaining any
amount of hypertrophy now
one thing to kind of keep in mind here
you can look at some pretty crazy models
from animals
and mice and cats and stuff and you can
see an increase in muscle length
but those typically happen with extreme
scenarios like
the dog example where you cut one muscle
out entirely or
you hang a muscle for 30 straight days
and you come back and it's longer
okay so that's probably not explaining
resistance exercise induced
muscle hypertrophy those are extreme
examples animal research casting and
things like that
however increases in diameter
are extremely well understood so this
being the muscle fiber themselves
we call this scientifically radial
growth right so there'll be longitudinal
length growth now this is radial growth
or csa cross-sectional area here and out
i'm basically just going to call it
diameter or csa
but the term technically would be radial
growth okay uh i i can't even explain to
you how
well this is understood or how well this
is documented really really clear that
if you just look at the cross-sectional
area the muscle fibers
eight weeks after you know into training
or something 12 weeks in whatever
you're going to see an increase in
diameter what we don't know though is
explicitly how that diameter is
increasing so that's what we're going to
go into now
option one would be to increase the
number of fibers
so the muscle cell gets bigger could we
just have simply more
muscle fibers so that would look like
this right so if you take your
image there you've got four muscle
fibers you add a fifth well just by
doing that you've increased the diameter
of the entire muscle itself
independent of even changing the
diameter of the muscles themselves the
muscle fibers themselves
okay so now unfortunately
this is the hyperplasia thing right now
every textbook basically in the world
is going to tell you hyperplasia is the
myth it doesn't
happen doesn't exist i remember being
taught that
in exercise physiology class in 2000 or
whatever
and i also remember sitting there
thinking hmm
i don't know if i'd buy it so i've
always been
a skeptic of hyperplasia being
impossible
the difficulty in this field has always
been how do you know
you're going to have to take every
muscle fiber out of someone's leg
count them all then do your training
somehow
on maybe the other leg and then take all
the muscle fibers out of that and count
them all that's the only way you would
know whether or not the number of fibers
increased in total
and so it's not something that's been
shown to not be true it's just something
that's been
almost impossible to actually study well
people have actually done that
in cats and stuff and shown the number
does go up and there's some other
information i'll get to in a second
so i've always been skeptical of it
you've heard me for now over 10 years on
podcasts and stuff being like ah
and being really coy with most
hyperplasia
and so let's go ahead and get into what
we know and talk more specifically about
that
right now so one option you could
increase fiber number is through this
hyperplasia now that specifically means
growing a new fiber okay now that
would look like this so that's one
muscle fiber right there you would have
to grow an entirely new one
all right if you go back to our original
image here
it would look kind of like this you've
got in this particular example
what uh 24 or so muscle fibers
well you would have to grow new ones
like that
okay that probably doesn't happen
certainly not with exercise when you're
a kid of course and you're developing
like my daughter right now but she
doesn't have all the muscle fibers now
that she will but
when she becomes a mature adult but in
terms of like a strength training
adaptation
it's probably extremely unlikely for a
bunch of reasons that you'll grow a new
fiber entirely
but what's possible is you could do what
we call fiber splitting
so instead of growing a new fiber
here right you take an individual fiber
and you split it in half and those two
actually turn into two of their own
independent fibers so the total number
of fibers goes up but not from growing a
whole new one
but splitting the ones you currently
have in half and then those things
regaining their size
so what you're seeing actually is an
image there of a real muscle fiber doing
just that
now in reality that's probably not
what's happening you'd probably just
smash it with my tweezers or something
but that's in theory what it would look
like
if a muscle fiber was splitting and
turning into two new
individual fibers as i mentioned though
this has been shown before
so this is the classic study from 1977
in cats where they showed this pretty
clearly in fact
he's a very famous muscle physiologist
showed this multiple times done a ton of
great work
in the 70s and 80s on things like this
also more updated more recently a couple
years ago just last year rather
my friend kevin muric at university of
kentucky
also and just a master of muscle
hypertrophy stuff
has shown pretty clearly a new review
article that i think is open access
muscle fiber splitting happens with
extreme loading in animals
so you can go and read that article more
if you want
but this is what it would look like so
this is an actual image from kevin's
paper
you can see one muscle fiber there doing
what we call
branching or splitting or fragmenting
okay it's not hyperplasia
but it's going from one it's splitting
off and generating
into a couple of ones other ways you can
see the images here where those
pink ish arrows are pointing to you or
the different um
again images that kevin has shown in
that paper of a fiber splitting and
generating into a new one
and then in the corner over here you can
actually see it's colored in it's quite
a bit larger and that's
splitting and developing into its own
new fiber so
we have seen this pretty clearly as far
as we can understand it
happening quite a bit in animal models
with the extreme loading
the difficulty of course
does it happen in humans well we
actually do have some evidence that it
does this is
this is uh from erickson's group and
this is a very famous powerlifting and
steroid study
but you can see that that's exactly what
they identified this fiber doing right
there
and so they do make the case for fiber
splitting being a function
in being a function of strength training
in humans again with the caveat though
being
they're not exactly normal folks and
they were having some help
so i'm actually jumping i'm going to
show you the key points of the take
homes from kevin's review article
but it basically said this hyperplasia
probably
sorry fiber splitting probably happens
with extreme loading now defining what
we mean by extreme loading is
not easy what that what relevance that
has to humans
we don't know right but it's probably
not pathological so in other words we do
see fiber splitting in muscle disease
and wasting
but we have now seen it in things that
are not necessarily muscle wasting so
it's not pathological
and we think it can occur in humans
especially with extensive use of
exogenous steroids
so that's kind of what we know about
fiber spitting fact you can see the last
point though that i don't have
highlighted that it's
the extent to which you get fiber
splitting versus like a bonafide
hyperplasia actually growing a new fiber
that's probably not occurring much
and not well understood here
so we don't know all right so at minimum
though i think we have to retune the way
that we speak about this though and
instead of saying like hyperplasia is
impossible this is not something we do
i think we can say something like
myofiber hyperplasia or probably more
appropriate i should have changed this
to my fiber splitting
it's not impossible but it is probably
very uncommon
i don't think in 12 weeks of training
you would see an appreciable number of
fiber splitting
and 10 years of training i honestly
think you would i think you would have
more fibers after 10 years of consistent
training
than you would before you pile on
steroids oh and i definitely think
you're going to have
an increase in total fiber number so if
we come back to our scorecard here
we probably do this all right most
likely you're not doing hyperplasia
fiber splitting we don't know so in
general an increase in fiber number
yeah i don't know probably not a lot
going on there
but we'll see so then what is explaining
our increase in
muscle diameter if it's not coming from
an increasing number of fibers
enter fiber size and that would be this
right
so you take the four fibers that you
have in this particular image you don't
make them longer
you don't add new fibers on you just
take what you have and you make them
thicker
okay so if we go back to our description
here by
um you know kent jorgensen and troy and
his lab
you can see that the longitudinal growth
we explained over there and this would
be your myofiber splitting that we
talked about being
probably unlikely but a being the far
more common finding so simply increasing
the diameter of the muscle cell
there and again as i mentioned at the
very beginning of the diameter talk here
this is very very very well documented
right so it's a big one
okay so this could be coming from an
increase in sarcomeres in parallel
okay so this is what we talked about
before stacking them on top would
increase the diameter there that's not
explained by simply increasing the
length which would have been explained
in our length
section so increases in circling and
parallel following ree have actually
never been shown that i'm aware of
in humans i know this is probably in
your textbook i know it's in a lot of
certification exams
i see people talk about this all the
time as if it's just like
oh we know that you can increase
sarcomere in series or in parallel and
it's specifically in parallel
i don't think i've ever seen it i mean i
would love
it be like a little impromptu challenge
here if someone can find a human study
that they use strength training right
not myopathy not disease
healthy folks and you actually not that
they cited somebody else's work because
this is what happens
they'll write it and they're just like
oh we know what happens a parallel site
somebody else and you go to that
citation you're like
they cited somebody else and you trace
all their background who the hell
actually showed it
so if you can find the thing where they
actually showed in a study
i'll give you a special prize and like a
major
shout out in the next video or something
i don't know whatever you want to do
okay so it's tough to actually see and
show
there so we still don't know exactly how
those term fibers are getting bigger
even though we know it's coming from the
level of the fiber
i'll go even farther farther to say that
the myofiber hypertrophy
is by far the most long-standing and
widely acknowledged contributor
to resistance exercise that's re induced
muscle hypertrophy right
in fact we we see typically like after
eight
to 16 weeks a 10 to 30 or so percent
increase in the mild fiber now if you go
back a few minutes we talked about how
much your muscle actually grows
you can see that these numbers don't
line up and they never will and i'll
talk about that scaling problem later
okay but the muscle fibers themselves
grow
a pretty good amount with a short amount
of strength training
and so that what numbers are we talking
about andy um you can look at it there
depending on kind of the lab and stuff
you look at the general size is around
4000 to 6000 or so in cross section area
and a 10 to 30 percent bump then would
then take you to like the 5 to 8
8 500 um micrometer range right so
that's what we're looking for i don't
know what for whatever reason i get
emails
all the time about people asking me like
what's the actual size of the fiber
so there you go i'm going to point you
to this video from now on
like i said a 20 to 30 increase in mild
fiber size or muscle fiber size is not
uncommon
but that would never translate into a 30
increase in the muscle cross-sectional
area
we don't see that happening okay so for
a bunch of reasons
um again a 30 increase in whole muscle
size would be a big big jump
in fact i'll say this differently in the
studies that do them both
so maybe they looked at the actual
muscle size or the mri and they took a
biopsy
the numbers are never the same okay so
there's a missing link there somehow
which we have to then
interpret this stuff with some caution
okay but as i mentioned
strength training does preferentially
target the fastest fibers but not always
there is some inconsistency in the quite
a bit actually of inconsistency in the
literature there
but i'd say generally it it probably
looks like that's what happens
um and i would argue it's actually
because the molecular machinery
which i talked more about in part number
two is much more abundant and sensitive
in those fast stretch fibers
okay so the quick version there is the
genes
the signaling activity and all the
things that sense and tell the fiber
as well as the machinery that allow it
to actually build more proteins
it's just more concentrated more
sensitive in those fast stretch fibers
so i do believe there's a molecular
rationale that suggests
it's not necessarily a nerve activation
issue although that's a problem too
but it is simply inherent to the
different fiber types as a
characteristic
difference between them
all right well
if that's true then there is some
speculation to things like
all right could there possibly be a fast
twitch versus slow choice
specific rep range in other words
there are some studies that have
suggested or hinted and there's been
some commentaries
saying it's possible that say
repetitions
of you know five to ten percent
cause more of a fast twitch fiber
hypertrophy but like set to 25 to 30
would be more slow twitch specific
it's not the worst rationale ever uh
indirect stuff has shown it
but more recent studies have shown it
maybe doesn't happen and so i think at
this point we don't know
we need more research in this area it
needs to be replicated from several
laboratories
because methodology matters so much so
right now we don't know but it's
something that's possible
that we could look into in the future so
to recap where we're at
we know the muscle muscle itself gets
larger in diameter we know that is
explained almost exclusively by an
increase in fiber size
how is the fiber actually getting larger
let's go even further down that road
one potential option is what we call
myofibril hypertrophy
okay and i explained that briefly
earlier but let's go into the literature
there
right we know the fibers get larger but
we don't know how
so if we come back to our picture here
this is what it would look like
okay so no increase in muscle
and number of muscle fibers that thing
is off the table right
it's probably this the myofibrils
themselves get larger
and because of that the space they smash
up against the muscle cell the muscle
cell then has to respond
by increasing its diameter well if we
replicated that throughout the entire
cell
we would get all smashed up together and
so the entire cell and the entire muscle
rather would have to get larger if all
the cells are getting larger so that
would explain
possibly why the whole muscle gets
larger while the muscle fiber gets
larger
if the myofibrils themselves are in fact
getting larger
you follow me okay does it happen
so this is what we call an increase in
protein accretion so this means more
proteins going
to the mild fiber now at this point
go take a break go work out go do
something different
right because we've really got to pay
attention when i start talking myofiber
myofilament myofibril
as far as i understand uh
we've got a lot well no not as far as
understanding we do have a lot of
studies i got a little hell on myself
sorry
we have a lot of studies showing protein
accretion happens in the myofiber
so it's not hard for us to do a study
where we use things like tracers and
infusions of amino acids
we put them in your blood we take a
muscle biopsy
we look at the muscle and we can count
the amount of those
that protein that we put in your blood
how much that got created in
into the muscle fiber and we have a lot
of studies this is called acute protein
synthesis
showing okay yeah we get a ton of
protein in the myofiber
okay so what about the myofibrils again
we actually have a good amount of
evidence
showing acute protein synthesis in the
myofibrils themselves
so we know that happens we know it's
acute unfortunately we don't have
any that i know of really well i think
one
right showing a chronic increase
in myofibril hypertrophy so we assume it
happens because we know
what happens at the whole muscle fiber
we know the myofibrils acutely will
bring in that protein we then just
assume it's actually going to happen in
the long term
the only study we actually have is from
and they basically said hey look we
think it's happening in the myofibrils
and therefore it has to be coming from
an increase in the myofilaments the
actin and myosin
so going back to here this is where the
assumption would come from right the act
on myosin
so if we look at the muscle cell more
specifically in diving in
we can see that we have three what we
call contractile
elements here's right so they act in a
myosin as well as the myofibril
themselves are all lumped together and
they're called what we call contractile
elements and the just the active myosin
itself are the myofilaments and this
distinction is going to be important
here when we start talking about
my research so if we dive in a little
bit more detailed in the myofibrils
here's what we're talking about as i
mentioned
we don't just have one set of actin
myosin in the myofibril you have a bunch
of them
one of the things that could possibly
happen to explain an increase in
myofibril size
is increasing the amount of myosin and
actin you have
so this is almost like a hyperplasia if
you will
of myofilaments if you did that the
diameter of the myofibril would have to
go larger
this is not an increase in muscle cells
no hyperplasia
it's not fiber splitting okay it's not
an increase in the number of myofibrils
it's an increase in the diameter of the
myofibrils
via increase in the number of myophilums
language is important here right if you
did that then the diameter of the
myofibrils would have to
actually go up so like we said
we don't have a lot of evidence joint
suggesting that
this actually happens we know that a
cute thing happens with more protein
coming in but we don't have
anything there however we do have a
really nice
recent theory from that cell paper right
in 2020 that says okay
we don't know exactly how this happens
we have virtually no evidence
but in theory this is what could happen
it could be either a b or c
so you could be taking the sarcomere and
you could start adding new myofilaments
and green here
in the middle you could kind of add them
longitudinally
like you're seeing there or you could
just start taking them and stacking them
on the
ends or the outside more like that
right so you take them right there and
you add them to the outside now
personally i believe that's the
strongest case i feel like if you did
options b or c you're going to screw
with the ability of the sarcomere to
contract properly
but adding them to the outside i think
is more plausible
again this is a theory a hypothesis at
best really
or is is the probably appropriate term
because we don't really know what's
happening there okay
so if we come back to our scorecard we
know this happens but we're working on a
lot of the details
on the pro the contractile protein
accretion okay
but something is at play most likely
there
another option we have is called
sarcoplasmic hypertrophy
okay so if we go back to our images here
and remember
at the very beginning these videos i
talked about my friend chris there and
then
my other this random friend i think his
name was ryan or
ronnie or something like that anyways
let's talk about bodybuilding versus
powerlifting because chris is actually
more of a powerlifter and strong man
well we know that if you do say classic
bodybuilding training
that you will get stronger and you will
add muscle but you won't add as much
strength
as a power lifter in fact if you did
power lifting training you would add
muscle
but you wouldn't add as much muscle as a
bodybuilder
so how's this possible how is it
possible that a bodybuilder
could have as much and probably in fact
almost certainly
more muscle than a power lifter
but they didn't get stronger or even as
strong i got strong
but not as strong don't you dare say
neuromuscular
don't you dare say neurological have
shame on you i am a muscle guy these are
muscle videos
we're not talking about that damn
nervous system
right stop giving it all the credit
well people have been saying for decades
maybe this is because there are
different types of muscle growth
so a bodybuilding style of training
causes a different type of hypertrophy
and maybe that hypertrophy is not as
functional
and powerlifting style of training
causes a different type of hypertrophy
that is more associated with strength
gains
and enter sarcoplasmic hypertrophy
okay so we would call this
functional growth and this would be
non-functional growth
okay so if we come back to our images
here what we see happen is if you did
the chris
more powerlifting style of training it
was more functional that would probably
come from an increase in myofilament or
something contractile right so if you
added more contractile elements you're
going to get stronger
period so perhaps that style of training
causes that type of hypertrophy
where the bodybuilding style of training
means you grow
you grew diameter of the muscle fibers
but not by adding more contractile units
something else could be explaining the
increase in diameter for example
it comes from what we call sarcoplasmic
in this definition
we're not really talking about like the
sarcoplasmic reticulum we're talking
about all things
non-contractile so all things
non-myofiber
or myofilament so mitochondria the sr
water creatine connective tissue
glycogen all that stuff would be lumped
together
and we would just simply call that a
sarcoplasmic
or non-contractile hypertrophy
back to cody and mike and they're famous
stuff they've done
really nice work in this area in the
last couple of years published several
studies
and this is another really easy review
to read if you want to learn more about
sarcoplasmic hypertrophy and the latest
research so i'll summarize it
here but basically if you add protein
you're going to add water and that's not
the question
in other words even if you do this
contractile
dysfunctional type the crystal more
power lifting style you add contractile
protein
that's going to come with an increase in
water in the cell
right we talked about a big chunk 75 of
the muscle fiber itself is water
and you can't just pack more protein in
there without adding more water
it would screw the way the muscle works
so that is really really really clear
scientifically what's less clear is this
what caused the increase in myofiber
cross-sectional area
sarcoplasmic hypertrophy is what we call
adding
disproportionate amounts of
non-contractile versus contractile
so in this example theoretically if you
did the strength training with chris
moore
you would add the same proportion of
protein contractile elements that you
added water
that you normally had right so
everything just got bigger no change in
proportion
what the sarcoplasmic hypertrophy
suggests is a disproportional increase
in fluid
or non-contractile stuff relative to
contractile
so you could still be adding protein but
you would just be adding a greater
percentage of your gains coming from
these non-contractile elements
right now this would be mostly fluid but
it could be again other things like
connective tissue
and stuff like that alright so equal
proteins plus fluid
explains chris moore where
disproportionate explains sarcoplasmic
hypertrophy
now people have been speculating about
this for
you know again probably since the 80s
and no one had really studied it in
depth until just the last few years with
mike roberts in his lab
so this is what we're talking about okay
imagine a muscle cell here
during your normal myofibril expansion
okay so again this is a
myofibril you've got the circle there
and it needs to increase its diameter
okay so what you see is a packing in of
more protein
and because more protein got in there
they said hey we got to have more water
and then water comes
in increases the diameter to keep the
proportions of protein
water the same here when it was small
as it was there normal spacing okay
now with the sarcoplasmic version it
would be the opposite
where you started off here something
happened and
the muscle cells started holding water
and then because it had
additional space it was able to then
build in more proteins
and so really we have a bit of a chicken
and an egg situation here
what's driving the increase in the cell
size is it the fact you've added more
protein
and now you've got to add more water to
maintain spacing
or do you add the water first give your
muscle a lot of space and a lot of room
making it really easy for you to build
in some more protein
that's kind of where we're at and what
we don't know chicken or egg what
happens first
of course mike and his team are probably
arguing a little bit more for the latter
right now where
many other folks would add for the
former
if it's me personally i actually think
mike is dead on here
i think this is exactly what happens for
a whole host of reasons
i'm not going to get into i think that
the water thing happens first
uh it makes the sense when you add this
up i'll talk about it in part two
but the acute exercise swelling our
muscle
exercise induced muscle swelling and
things like that we know water goes in
really really really quickly
and so i think that to me makes a lot
more sense
but anyways tbd
okay so
again it could be equal growth the
evidence suggests
right now that you probably have that
equal growth
between protein and water in other words
the contractile thing i'll put it this
way the current evidence
probably most strongly suggests
sarcoplasmic hypertrophy
is not a predominant explanation but
it's growing so depending on who you
listen to you may think the evidence is
strong you may think it's incredibly
weak
or maybe somewhere in between so right
now i do have to admit it's not super
strong
but it's moving
it's a lot stronger than it was two
years ago a lot stronger than it was
five years ago
okay i guess one way to think about it
is this um
this is the adaptation like the chris
moore thing is the adaptation right
you're trying to grow more protein so
you can have more contraction that's the
point
the sarcoplasmic thing is probably the
thing that's maintaining space so if i'm
being honest i think both
clearly happen and i think it probably
happens as a result of different types
of training different insults
and different stimuli part two stuff i
also think it probably happens
differently at different phases of
training
when you're untrained versus somewhat
trained versus extremely highly trained
i think it happens probably a little bit
both right
right but like i said at this point um
it doesn't look like
most hypertrophy is driven because of
sarcoplasmic
but we'll see all right another way to
think about this is it's
it could possibly this is totally
hypothesizing
the initial response to novel training
could be the circuit positive approach
so you go out and you do something
different you do a rep range
if you do a style training you haven't
done in a while you're going to get a
lot of water
swelling into the cell so that initial
response could be hyper it could be
sarcoplasmic
then kind of four five six weeks later
you start to build in the proteins at
that point you're now more in a
contractile
years go by though i do think that at
some point you're going to reach kind of
a
maximum capacity for the protein and any
further increases past
that are going to come from sarcoplasmic
so it may not be as simple as like this
one versus that one in fact physiology
almost never works that way
all right so i think this is probably
more the story um
than we know it's also possible the bro
scientists were right
all along in the fact that um you know
maybe the sarcoplasmic reticulum or
sarcoplasmic hypertrophies
is really more of a function of like
really high volume training
and a moderate to lower volume isn't
enough to actually cause
that abnormal amount of fluid increase
those are all very very possible in fact
i really like the theoretical outline
that mike
laid out here in cody in their article
which is like okay maybe pre-training
muscle fiber down here
okay over here you've got myofibril
number as well as cross-sectional area
perhaps years of training go by and then
at some point
you reach the cellular myofibrillar
accretion threshold right so in other
words you can't pack any more protein up
here
so at that point your myofibril number
can't go any higher
and if you want to further increase your
muscle size it's going to have to come
through fluid retention so that's kind
of what i just explained and i think
it's
it's a nice little theory with all
theories we want to see data
but and there's some rationale now it's
not too bad
to close the book on this sarcoplasmic
hypertrophy as we understand it now this
is probably what it looks like
potentially contractile induced cypriot
is more of a function of high load where
sarcoplasmic
is a high volume issue and this could
explain why we see
for example some studies show a very
close relationship between increases in
strength and hypertrophy if so that's
probably then
they probably experience contractile
growth other studies
show the opposite very little or at best
moderate relationship between increasing
muscle growth
and increasing strength and that could
be explained by the fact that their
growth was
a different style it didn't have
contractile elements to it
okay so when we close the book on
sarcoplasmic i'd say that
the check mark is a lot smaller than it
is like protein accretion
the evidence is much stronger in there
and we still have a lot of questions
to work out there so we don't know a lot
of the details
okay like i said equal protein
and sarcoplasmic growth would be there
as well
as there moving forward then eventually
we have to come to
some understanding what the hell is
actually growing in the muscle so we
talked about that one single study
with myofibrillar hyper myofibular
hypertrophy
and they basically said look it's got to
be coming from the myofilaments so what
do we know about that myofilaments
well one thing that could also be
happening is this
if you took a myofibril and you
increased
those new myofilaments like we talked
about before
and we talked about how we can maybe add
them to the edge well eventually that
thing is going to get bigger
and that's going to get bigger and that
myofibril's going to get bigger
well just like we talked about with the
muscle fibers continuing to get bigger
and eventually they split and we call
that muscle fiber splitting
one thing that could happen is the
myofibers themselves could split
so enter myofibular splitting not
mild fiber no muscle cell splitting but
the myofibrils themselves so as a result
of that if you continue to expand by
adding new myofilaments
acne myosin you could eventually cause a
splitting of the myofibrils
which mean you would eventually have
myofibular splitting
not myofibular genesis so in other words
you're not just creating new myofibers
out of nowhere
just like we talked about with the
muscle fibers you're now just taking
them out of fibrils
and splitting them probably because they
reach that threshold of protein
accretion right
too many active myosin you kept packing
them in there and eventually said that's
it we're splitting
into two new myofibrils so i'll go back
to a nice image that mike and
cody did in their review paper but they
said basically this okay if myofibrils
are the thing that's growing
we have several options option over here
in the middle
is the myofibrils continue to get
thicker by adding myofilaments to the
outside
this is that image right here
right okay so we add more yellow parts
to the outside
or what we could be doing with
sarcoplasmic expansion is just adding a
few
of these additional mod fibers to the
outside
or could be that right so this image and
this image are kind of the same but here
they're saying
you know you keep the total amount
fairly low because it's mostly fluid
increase
where here you are getting a noticeable
increase in total amount of myofibrils
probably because the myofilaments
themselves got too thick
we don't have a lot of information on
this yet it's a working hypothesis
so we'll come back to you later but what
it would look like is this
boom there we go so remember in the
previous one we talked about hyperplasia
of the muscle fibers we put in new
fibers in white out here
in this particular case again we're
probably not
growing new myofibrils myofibril genesis
we are simply taking these yellow ones
and these yellow ones get so big they
eventually have to split
into two okay so it would kind of look
like this right
in general you would have your radial
myofibular hyperplasia
which you can see in the corner over
there compare that to your radial
myofibrillar hypertrophy
and that probably explains most of
what's going on and again i should
probably change that
myo radial myofibular splitting that's
probably what's really happening
so what's our research look like on
monofibular hyperplasia
well we don't have any there are a
couple of studies that have been done in
the heart
and they show what happens there so a
lot of people do think that this happens
we just haven't shown it in skeletal
muscle yet we certainly haven't shown it
as a result of
strength training or lifting weights but
most people think that
based on all the information i've shown
you the acute stuff
the protein accretion stuff the fact
we've seen it actually happen in heart
that it's a very likely
outcome and the nice part is i feel like
i've been talking to you for an hour
about things we don't know yet
well things are changing the advent of
really nice advanced laser microscopes
you can see you picture that there
shooting it into a muscle fiber we
should be having a lot of answers soon
so technology
imaging technology is greatly improving
and the cost is really coming down
uh i mean in the last couple of years so
we're going to have some
some more information on this i'm going
to definitely have to redo this video in
a couple of years
without question all right so if we go
to our last marker here
myofibular hyperplasia or splitting
again we know it probably happens
but we're working out a lot of the
details behind it there right
it's mostly unknown that's why i put the
question mark first
on this one it's mostly unknown but i
think probably
that's gonna happen there all right
so now what i want to do is kind of
finish this section on a nice big
summary
so this is a reproduced kind of image
from troy and stu's paper
so let's take you say you take that
muscle fiber you did some strength
training
what are the possible options this is a
nice summary of what we talked about
at the macroscopic level either one of a
few things two things happened
you had that longitudinal fascicle
growth
or you had radio fascicle growth and we
have good scientific evidence
to suggest both happen okay what
explains that macroscopic group we've
got to go to the microscopic growth
now it could be coming the from the
radial fascicle growth
it could be coming from a radial
increase in myofibrillar growth
we've seen that a billion times right
it could be coming from myofibrils or
splitting although we don't have a lot
of evidence there
i think it does happen though especially
steroids
and or also it could be coming from
muscle fiber hyperplasia which is
probably just
not in the cards for a normal adaptation
in terms of the longitudinal side um we
don't know
much detail there again we know what
happens the fascicle but whether or not
the fiber itself gets longer
and we know that the muscle the whole
muscle itself generally is not getting
longer so
we don't know and i'm not sure how you
would ever figure out the fiber length
issue so what explains these things
at the ultra-structural level when we
look at the radial growth or the
increase in diameter the muscle fibers
could be possibly coming from
myofibrillar hyperplasia
we don't know a lot there we don't have
a ton of evidence but it's
it seems likely it seems very plausible
could be myofibular hypertrophy and
again
we have pretty strong indication
although not a lot of direct but that's
happening
a very strong case for that and then
also could be sarcoplasmic hypertrophy
and the case for that is a lot weaker
mostly an unknown but it's growing and
building
and then of course from longitudinal
stuff since we don't know if the fiber
is getting longer
we don't know if the myofibrils are
getting longer either
okay and i mentioned this a little bit
um throughout the thing but just to make
sure we're on the same page here is we
do have to be careful when we're looking
at these different levels right
so i just got done talking about the
macroscopic microscopic and ultra
structural levels
and they don't scale perfectly so an
increase in 30 percent protein synthesis
would never ever actually result in 30
percent increase in
things so don't take a study that showed
hey this type of training
increase protein synthesis by 25 percent
and think you're going to have 25
growth your muscle or even at the
fiber level we don't see those things
happen in fact we've known this for a
long time
we tend to get excited in the science
and we forget about this but
in 1967 gordon one another really
famous and well cited muscle researcher
said
there is a quote unquote complete
disassociation between whole muscle
and fiber size and trained animals
all right so just be careful in scaling
and we also saw the same thing here in
that classic original study right
they warned of the same thing right so
we saw 50 increases in muscle size and
that didn't line up with the actual
changes
in the muscle fibers all right
in fact in this particular case what we
typically see happen is
the muscle fibers will grow a lot more
than the actual muscles so
you might see a 26 percent increase in
muscle fiber size
that would only result in 13 increase in
actual
whole muscle growth okay now
if you want this is a summary table from
that article i've been using this entire
way
and they talk about not only that the
the ways that muscle could possibly grow
the strength of the evidence as well as
the specific gaps in the knowledge
and so this is up there for you if you
again the article is free they'll open
access so you can go look at it in your
own if you want
but just to kind of summarize the thing
we know the fibers change pinnation
angle
or lengthen potentially by adding
sarcomeres though we don't know
we know hyper fiber hyperplasia and
splitting is unlikely
especially hyperplasia and we know fiber
hypertrophy by increasing sarcoplasmic
or contractile and those could be
myofibular hyperplasia
or hypertrophy or myofiber splitting
probably
elements it's probably what explains
most of hypertrophy
so now that you understand a little bit
more
about what muscle hypertrophy actually
is you can go watch
part two and part three so you can learn
how
what you need to actually do to maximize
the growth
but before i leave you
i have a challenge for you this is a
very complicated field and i'm not
perfect
and so in general i appreciate this with
all of my videos i just want to make
sure i'm emphasizing it more
challenge number one tell me where i'm
messed up if you think i i did
not if i used the wrong word and accent
and then corrected it and it's not what
i care about
but if you've got evidence to suggest
i'm wrong in something or
a new study has come out keep in mind
the time
so don't like bring up a video came out
after this or a study became my athens
video came out and i can't do much about
that
but i would love to know where i'm wrong
or what other information i've got
that always helps and then my second
challenge is this i want you to share
the three most interesting things you
learned with three new people
including me right so i love to hear
what parts
i just dropped the ball on with my
explanation to a part you're like i
didn't get this at all
as well as the things you found super
interesting maybe i'll make more videos
shorter videos more specific on the
areas that people found
most interesting so you can do that on
youtube instagram twitter
whereves let me know what you found the
most interesting
okay hope you enjoyed this this was a
ton of work for me but i thoroughly
thoroughly
enjoyed it myself so hopefully you can
feel that coming through
i'm really excited for you to dive into
the next section which is part two the
newest science
on the mechanisms or the things that
stimulate muscle growth
right and it's changed in the last
couple of years so as always
i significantly and massively appreciate
all of your support
i have like the highest rated percentage
of
good jobs and stuff on youtube and it's
history and that's not true but it's
super high in it i'm always thankful for
that
so yeah there you go enjoy go get swole
get your big going
[Music]
you